<document>
 <title>The Collapse of Political Trust</title>
 <author>Jonah Lehrer</author>
 <published><date>July 27, 2011</date><time>5:40 pm</time></published>
 <categories>
  <category>Frontal Cortex</category>
  <category>Science Blogs</category>
 </categories>

 <body>
  <section>
   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>American politics makes me sad.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>One can’t help but imagine the history books of the future,
    highlighting this moment as an example of why the decline began, how a
    country this rich and free developed such a dysfunctional political
    system.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>But this post is not a lament for a bygone politics, because
    lord knows there are enough of those.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>Instead, I think the current breakdown in Washington
    highlights the fragility of a human capability we’ve long taken for
    granted: trust.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>While economists have begun focusing on trust as a crucial
    factor in economic development – a country without trust can’t build the
    institutions that make growth possible – trust is also an essential
    component of effective politics.</s>
    <s rank='.3'>Democracies, after all, depend on compromise.</s>
    <s rank='.3'>And compromise requires trust.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>At the moment, the neuroscience of trust remains extremely
    provisional.</s>
    <s rank='.4'>We still don’t know why some societies are awash in trust
    while others are forced to do without, subsisting on nothing but the
    instinctive faith in close friends and family.</s>
    <s rank='.4'>We don’t know why some people are so much more trusting than
    others or what happens when the bonds of trust are broken.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>Nevertheless, there have been some interesting glimmers into
    the formation of trust in the brain.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>Consider this elegant investigation of trust, led by Brooks
    King-Casas, Colin Camerer, Read Montague, et. al.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>The research was born out of a serious limitation of
    conventional fMRI, which looks at the individual brain in splendid
    isolation.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>(A subject is put in a claustrophobic scanner and told to
    perform a task.)</s>
    <s rank='.3'>Humans, of course, are a social species – our behavior is
    often influenced by the behavior of others – so the scientists pioneered a
    technique known as hyper-scanning, which allows subjects in different fMRI
    machines to interact in real time.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.2'>The experiment revolved around a simple economic game in which
    getting the maximum reward required the strangers to trust one another.</s>
    <s rank='.3'>However, if one of the players grew especially selfish, he or
    she could always steal from the pot and erase the tenuous sense of
    trust.</s>
    <s rank='.4'>By monitoring the players’ brains, the scientists were able to
    predict whether or not someone would steal money several seconds before the
    theft actually occurred.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>The secret was a cortical area known as the caudate nucleus,
    which closely tracked the payouts from the other player.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>(The caudate is usually discussed in the context of addiction,
    since it plays a central role in modulating our expectation of
    pleasure.)</s>
    <s rank='.1'>Montague noticed that whenever the caudate exhibited reduced
    activity, trust tended to break down.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>But what exactly is the caudate computing?</s>
    <s rank='.1'>How do we decide whom to trust with our money?</s>
    <s rank='.6'>At first, the caudate didn’t get excited until the subjects
    actually trusted one another and garnered their separate rewards.</s>
    <s rank='.6'>But over time this brain area started to expect those rewards,
    so that it fired long before the money actually arrived.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>It’s only at this point – once we take those future benefits
    for granted – that the bonds of trust between the players began to
    form.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.8'>The moral is that trust is ultimately about the expectation of
    rewards.</s>
    <s rank='.4'>We see trust as such a noble trait, but it’s ultimately rooted
    in a greedy calculation, emanating from our primal dopaminergic
    circuitry:</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.8'>Taken together, these results suggest that the head of the
    caudate nucleus receives or computes information about (i) the fairness of
    a social partner’s decision and (ii) the intention to repay that decision
    with trust.</s>
    <s rank='.5'>In early rounds of the game, the ”intention to trust” is
    evident only after an investment is revealed.</s>
    <s rank='.5'>With experience, this signal shifts to a time preceding the
    revelation of the investment.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.6'>In other words, we don’t trust people because they seem nice
    or virtuous or trustworthy, whatever those adjectives mean.</s>
    <s rank='.6'>We trust them because they get us the good stuff, delivering
    what Montague refers to as the “social juice” of reciprocity.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>When we say we trust someone, what we’re really saying is that
    they’re a reliable source of what we want.</s>
    <s rank='.4'>I scratch your back, you scratch mine.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>And this returns us to the present dysfunction in
    Washington.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>If trust is about the distribution of rewards – about learning
    to expect bonuses from others – then it’s going to be a lot harder to share
    those rewards in an age of scarcity and deficits.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>For the first time in decades, congresspeople aren’t trading
    pork barrel projects and tax breaks – they’re negotiating steep budget
    cuts.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>Those cuts might be necessary, but they’re aren’t going to
    excite the caudate or generate that requisite burst of “social juice.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>The traditional means of developing trust among Congresspeople
    have disappeared.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>There are, of course, myriad reasons for the increasing
    polarization of Congress.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>But I can’t help but wonder if one of the reasons has to with
    this newfound lack of favor trading, as it’s increasingly difficult for
    politicians to barter projects in exchange for votes.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>It’s easy to hate on Congressional pork and mock all those
    silly projects that get snuck into bills.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>But when we do without pork, we also deny our politicians a
    means of building trusting relationships across the aisle.</s>
    <s rank='.5'>In this sense, those bridges to nowhere are a sort of
    benevolent inefficiency, a form of waste that, just maybe, keeps us from
    becoming a banana republic.</s>
    <s rank='.1'>Such are the hazards of politics in age of cutting.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>If trust begins when we share the treasure, what happens when
    there’s no treasure left to share?</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>PS. I also love Bill Clinton’s theory that the extreme
    partisanship of Congress is largely due to…sleep deprivation.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>PPS. For more on the hidden benefits of Congressional pork,
    check out this paper by the political scientists John Ellwood and Eric
    Patashnik.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.1'>Image: President Barack Obama sits next to House Speaker John
    Boehner of Ohio, left, in the Cabinet Room of the White House, Saturday,
    July 23, 2011, in Washington, as they meet to discuss the debt. (AP
    Photo/Carolyn Kaster)</s>
   </p>
  </section>
 </body>
</document>
