<document
 src="http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2011/09/mcchrystal-network/">

 <title>How Special Ops Copied al-Qaida to Kill It</title>
 <author>Spencer Ackerman</author>
 <!--
  <time pubdate datetime="2011-09-09T06:30-05:00">
   September 9, 2011 6:30am
  </time>
 -->
 <published><date>September 9, 2011</date><time>6:30 am</time></published>
 <keywords>
  <keyword name='network' rank='.8'>Network</keyword>
 </keywords>

 <body>
  <section>
   <p>
    <s>One of the greatest ironies of the 9/11 Era: while politicians, generals
    and journalists lined up to denounce al-Qaida as a brutal band of fanatics,
    one commander thought its organizational structure was kind of
    brilliant.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>He set to work rebuilding an obscure military entity into a
    lethal, agile, secretive and highly <keyword
    name='network'>networked</keyword> command — essentially, the U.S.’ very
    own al-Qaida. It became the most potent weapon the U.S. has against another
    terrorist attack.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>That was the work of Stanley McChrystal.</s>
    <s>McChrystal is best known as the general who lost his command in
    Afghanistan after his staff shit-talked the Obama administration to Rolling
    Stone.</s>
    <s>Inescapable as that public profile may be, it doesn’t begin to capture
    the impact he made on the military.</s>
    <s>McChrystal’s fingerprints are all over the Joint Special Operations
    Command, the elite force that eventually killed Osama bin Laden.</s>
    <s>As the war on terrorism evolves into a series of global shadow wars,
    JSOC and its partners are the ones who wage it.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>These days, McChrystal travels around the country to talk about his
    leadership style.</s>
    <s>His insights reveal a lot about how the JSOC became the Obama team’s
    go-to counterterrorism group.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>“In bitter, bloody fights in both Afghanistan and Iraq,”
    McChrystal has written, “it became clear to me and to many others that to
    defeat a <keyword name='network'>networked</keyword> enemy we had to become
    a <keyword name='network'>network</keyword> ourselves.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal’s career also reveals a second irony: at the moment of his
    greatest ascension, to overall command in Afghanistan, McChrystal couldn’t
    take his own advice.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal declined to speak for this article.</s>
    <s>He’s working on a book, due out in 2012, that will probably shed some
    light on his tenure at JSOC.</s>
    <s>This piece is drawn from his speeches, interviews I’ve conducted over
    the years with special operations and intelligence veterans — usually off
    the record — as well as two insightful new books: Counterstrike by Thom
    Shanker and Eric Schmitt and Top Secret America by Dana Priest and William
    Arkin.</s>
   </p>
   </section>
   <section>
    <h1>The <keyword name='network'>Networked</keyword> Ninja</h1>

   <p>
    <s>The historical problem special operations forces had, in the eyes of
    high-level policymakers, is that they weren’t ninjas.</s>
    <s>U.S. commandos trained constantly, but they didn’t have much combat
    experience during the 1980s and 90s.</s>
    <s>When the Clinton administration reviewed its options for attacking
    al-Qaida’s Afghanistan safe houses in 1998, President Clinton vented
    frustration: “You know, it would scare the shit out of al-Qaida if suddenly
    a bunch of black ninjas rappelled out of helicopters into the middle of
    their camp.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>JSOC certainly knew how to rappel.</s>
    <s>The problem was it often didn’t know where to rappel, or where to send
    their helicopters, or who the enemy was.</s>
    <s>In 2002, a JSOC AC-130 helicopter gunship came to relieve a team of
    commandos who’d come under attack while hunting Taliban leaders in Uruzgan
    province.</s>
    <s>It opened fire so indiscriminately that the low estimate of civilian
    deaths is 48.</s>
    <s>Hundreds may have been killed.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>JSOC had minimal intelligence capabilities.</s>
    <s>The CIA, the agency that knew Afghanistan the best and led the hunt for
    al-Qaida, distrusted it.</s>
    <s>It was hived off from the conventional military, whose low-level
    commanders could be left to deal with angry civilians after one of JSOC’s
    raids in Afghanistan or Iraq.</s>
    <s>McChrystal took command in 2003, began examining al-Qaida, and had
    something of a revelation.</s>
   </p>

   <aside><s>We had to become a <keyword name='network'>network</keyword>
   ourselves.</s></aside>

   <p>
    <s>“[I]t became increasingly clear — often from intercepted communications
    or the accounts of insurgents we had captured — that our enemy was a
    constellation of fighters organized not by rank but on the basis of
    relationships and acquaintances, reputation and fame,” McChrystal
    remembered recently in Foreign Policy.</s>
    <s>“We realized we had to have the rapid ability to detect nuanced changes,
    whether the emergence of new personalities and alliances or sudden changes
    in tactics.”</s>
    <s>Think Bruce Wayne getting inspired by a bat to strike fear into the
    hearts of criminals.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal set to work, as he put it, building JSOC’s <keyword
    name='network'>network</keyword>.</s>
    <s>One key node: CIA.</s>
    <s>During a January speech, he recalled how he needed CIA’s help getting
    intelligence on a Taliban leader he was hunting.</s>
    <s>CIA was secretive, compartmentalized and suspicious of other
    organizations meddling in its affairs — exactly what JSOC used to be
    like.</s>
    <s>So McChrystal took the rare step of going to CIA headquarters, hat in
    hand.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>As it turned out, CIA just needed a promise that JSOC
    “wouldn’t go across the border” into Pakistan, jeopardizing its own
    operations.</s>
    <s>McChrystal agreed, the intel flowed, and the Taliban commander was
    killed.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>It was the beginning of a new relationship between JSOC and the vast spy
    apparatus the U.S. built after 9/11.</s>
    <s>CIA operatives and analysts would visit McChrystal’s base of operations
    in Balad, Iraq to plan joint missions.</s>
    <s>And not just them: satellite analysts from the National
    Geospatial-Intelligence Agency, regional experts from the State Department,
    and surveillance specialists from the National Security Agency were the
    next people McChrystal effectively recruited.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>McChrystal spent his commander’s discretionary fund not on
    better guns, but on purchasing bandwidth so that all the nodes of his
    <keyword name='network'>network</keyword> could speak to each other,
    sometimes during missions.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Veterans of JSOC remember that as crucial.</s>
    <s rank='.6'>An NSA-created linkup called the Real Time Regional Gateway
    allowed operatives who seized scraps of intelligence from raids — a
    terrorist’s cellphone contacts, receipts for bomb ingredients, even
    geolocated terrorist cellphones — to send their crucial data to different
    nodes across the <keyword name='network'>network</keyword>.</s>
    <s>One analyst might not appreciate the significance of a given piece of
    intel.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>But once JSOC effectively became an experiment in intel
    crowdsourcing, it soon got a bigger, deeper picture of the enemy it was
    fighting — and essentially emulating.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>“If you look at JSOC, you’re looking at arguably the single most
    integrated, most truly joint command within the U.S. military,” says Andrew
    Exum, who served in the Army’s Ranger Regiment in Iraq and Afghanistan in
    2003 and 2004 and who advised McChrystal as a civilian in 2009.</s>
    <s>McChrystal and his brain trust “were seeking to do and succeeding in
    doing what many commanders and diplomats and government officials talk
    about: tearing down the walls that exist between various departments,
    agencies and military units.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>It also helped mitigate JSOC’s most horrific mistakes.</s>
   </p>
   </section>

   <section>
    <h1>‘No Blood, No Foul,’ No More</h1>

   <p>
    <s>Defense Secretary Donald Rumsfeld gave JSOC the authority to hold
    prisoners for 90 days before transferring them to military detention
    facilities.</s>
    <s>That gave JSOC jailers nearly limitless authority over their
    captives.</s>
    <s>Unsurprisingly, some began abusing it, beating prisoners senseless in a
    facility called Camp Nama — which Saddam Hussein used as a torture chamber
    — where the slogan was, “No Blood, No Foul.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Although no public investigation has ever been conducted into the abuses
    at Nama, McChrystal reportedly said “This is how we lose” when he toured
    the facility for the first time.</s>
    <s>He assigned his top intelligence officer, then-Brig. Gen. Michael Flynn,
    to professionalize JSOC interrogations.</s>
    <s>Flynn reached out to trained interrogators throughout the U.S.
    bureaucracy and even to around the world to provide instruction.</s>
    <s>Subsequent interrogations of suspected al-Qaida captives in Iraq relied
    on Saudis brought in when a Saudi national was nabbed, Egyptians when an
    Egyptian was.</s>
    <s>Priest and Arkin report that detainees would even be videoconferenced in
    with their families — who’d plead with their sons to cooperate.</s>
   </p>

   <aside><s>This is how we lose.</s></aside>

   <p>
    <s>Think about that for a minute.</s>
    <s>JSOC is the most secretive organization in the U.S. military.</s>
    <s>Its detention and interrogation operations are among its most sensitive
    missions.</s>
    <s>And the family members of terrorist suspects actually got a glimpse
    inside them, all as a method of building rapport.</s>
    <s>Not only that, diplomats, NSA techs, intelligence analysts of all
    stripes and foreign government officials became, effectively, JSOC
    adjuncts, so JSOC could leverage their expertise.</s>
    <s>Despite years of post-9/11 lip service to breaking down bureaucratic
    barriers, JSOC actually did it, for the most important and secretive
    operations the military undertook.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.5'>Flynn was arguably McChrystal’s most important partner in
    building JSOC’s <keyword name='network'>network</keyword>.</s>
    <s>“We once had a problem in terms of how we were going to track our units
    on the ground using satellite technology.</s>
    <s>It’s almost unthinkable today because of GPS, Blue Force Tracker and so
    forth,” recalls Andrew Exum, now a senior fellow at the Center for a New
    American Security, referring to a GPS receiver system that allows U.S.
    troops to track the movements of their allies.</s>
    <s>“I remember Gen. Flynn’s solution was to track down a really smart
    engineer at Georgia Tech University, who developed a piece of software for
    use by commercial aircraft.</s>
    <s>It went outside the standard Army acquisition process — we’d still be
    waiting for the equivalent of Navstar if [Flynn] hadn’t.</s>
    <s>But the fact that he was comfortable interacting in the world outside of
    the military in order to achieve an effect says a lot about him.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal left JSOC in early 2008 to take a senior position working for
    Adm. Mike Mullen, the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>The <keyword name='network'>network</keyword> he built was
    getting results.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>In June 2006, JSOC killed al-Qaida’s leader in Iraq, Abu Musab
    al-Zarqawi.</s>
    <s>(McChrystal had Zarqawi’s corpse brought to his office for personal
    inspection.)</s>
    <s>During the Iraq surge, JSOC raided suspected terrorist safe houses on a
    nightly basis, something McChrystal’s friend David Petraeus would repeat in
    Afghanistan.</s>
    <s>McChrystal left JSOC in the hands of his friend and deputy, Vice Adm.
    William McRaven — and the conclusion, from President George W. Bush, that
    “JSOC is awesome.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>But McChrystal would never enjoy the same success again.</s>
   </p>
   </section>

   <section>
    <h1>The Un-<keyword name='network'>Networked</keyword> McChrystal</h1>

   <p>
    <s>Defense Secretary Robert Gates tapped McChrystal to lead the Afghanistan
    war in May 2009.</s>
    <s>JSOC veterans were thrilled.</s>
    <s>“The man is unstoppable,” wrote one, using the pseudonym Dalton
    Fury.</s>
    <s>“McChrystal has few peers and makes even fewer mistakes.”</s>
    <s>He was about to make a lot of them.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.5'>The McChrystal of JSOC enlisted people from across the
    bureaucracy into his <keyword name='network'>network</keyword>.</s>
    <s>That turned out to be much easier to do when running an organization
    comprised of only a few thousand people.</s>
    <s>Securing the buy-in of a multinational military coalition comprising
    140,000 was far more challenging.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal had early successes coaxing Afghan President Hamid Karzai,
    who resented the Obama administration’s arms-length relationship.</s>
    <s>“His approach to President Karzai was humility,” recalls Exum, who
    advised McChrystal that summer.</s>
    <s>“He had the attitude of, ‘I’m here to support you, the Afghan
    president.’”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Some in uniform weren’t so sure they enjoyed their commander’s
    support.</s>
    <s>McChrystal faced the unenviable task of curbing NATO’s accidental
    civilian deaths — he called Afghan public opinion “strategically decisive”
    —  while beating back an inflamed Taliban insurgency.</s>
    <s>Two of his earliest moves to that end inadvertently made his troops
    question his support.</s>
    <s>One was his August counterinsurgency guidance, which instructed troops
    to show outright deference to Afghans, down to giving them right of way on
    the roads.</s>
    <s>The other was his Tactical Directive, which sharply restricted the rules
    of engagement for combat aircraft, something that alarmed troops who feared
    a loss of crucial air support.</s>
   </p>

   <aside><s>I would love to kick McChrystal in the nuts.</s></aside>

   <p>
    <s>Both of those decisions were made for defensible reasons.</s>
    <s>Losing the support of Afghanistan’s people was more destructive to the
    war than losing any firefight to the Taliban.</s>
    <s>But McChrystal didn’t sufficiently sell his decisions to his own troops,
    explaining to them why they were ultimately in their interests.</s>
    <s>“I would love to kick McChrystal in the nuts,” a Special Forces veteran
    told Michael Hastings for his fateful McChrystal profile in Rolling
    Stone.</s>
    <s>“His rules of engagement put soldiers’ lives in even greater
    danger.”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.5'>There was something else missing from McChrystal’s <keyword
    name='network'>network</keyword>: the U.S.  embassy in Kabul.</s>
    <s>While McChrystal and Amb. Karl Eikenberry, a former Afghanistan war
    commander himself, supposedly enjoyed good relations, the embassy and NATO
    sometimes seemed like they weren’t in the same country.</s>
    <s>Then one of Eikenberry’s cables back to Washington casting doubt on
    McChrystal’s desired troop surge leaked to the press.</s>
    <s>That poisoned the well.</s>
    <s>“Here’s one that covers his flank for the history books,” McChrystal
    kvetched to Hastings.</s>
    <s>“Now if we fail, they can say, ‘I told you so.’”</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.6'>But the surge itself was causing a breach with the most
    important node in McChrystal’s <keyword name='network'>network</keyword>:
    the White House.</s>
    <s>In the 2009 debates over sending more troops to Afghanistan, President
    Obama reportedly felt like the military was boxing him into an unwise
    escalation.</s>
    <s>McChrystal, in London for one of his first public appearances, bluntly
    remarked that he thought all other strategies were doomed.</s>
    <s rank='.7'>Although McChrystal repeatedly defended the Obama team, the
    press went wild with a narrative about an insubordinate commander, and not
    without some justification.</s>
    <s>Obama ultimately endorsed the surge, but it was, at best, a Pyrrhic
    victory for McChrystal.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Nor were McChrystal’s battlefield moves showing the same success that
    JSOC had demonstrated.</s>
    <s>Through the summer and fall of 2009, Marines fought furiously through
    Helmand Province, for little obvious gain.</s>
    <s>That February, he and Karzai invaded the Helmand town of Marja,
    proclaiming that he had a “government in a box” ready to establish order in
    the cleared town.</s>
    <s>Instead, fighting continued for months, without a significant Afghan
    government presence.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.8'>All that meant that McChrystal, the consummate <keyword
    name='network'>networker</keyword>, was out of allies when Hastings quoted
    McChrystal’s aides making derogatory comments about the Obama team.</s>
    <s>Quick to defend his loyal staff and take responsibility, McChrystal
    immediately offered to resign.</s>
    <s>Obama took him up on it.</s>
    <s>A sterling career was unexpectedly over.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>People close to McChrystal were mystified by the uncharacteristic,
    self-marginalization.</s>
    <s>“In every review of COIN best practices, ‘unity of effort’ tops the
    list,” one of his advisers told Danger Room last year.</s>
    <s>“Every.</s>
    <s>Single.</s>
    <s>Review.</s>
    <s>And we’re totally fucking it up; fucking up the one thing that should be
    in our control.”</s>
    <s>The McChrystal of JSOC never needed to be reminded.</s>
   </p>
   </section>

   <section>
    <h1>The <keyword name='network'>Network</keyword> Strikes Back</h1>

   <p>
    <s>McChrystal and Obama have patched things up.</s>
    <s>Obama tapped McChrystal to spearhead a White House effort to support
    veterans’ families.</s>
    <s>McChrystal has never expressed public bitterness about losing his
    command, and even joked about his mistakes during his July 2010
    retirement.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Some close to McChrystal say that what hurt him the most is that he had
    to leave Afghanistan before he could implement a turnaround in the U.S.’
    fortunes.</s>
    <s>When his friend Petraeus took over the war, Petraeus reversed
    McChrystal’s restrictions on airpower, leading to the biggest aerial
    bombardment in the war thus far.</s>
    <s>Petraeus also relied on McChrystal’s protege McRaven at JSOC for a
    relentless pace of raids on Taliban forces.</s>
    <s>Only by the time Petraeus relinquished command in July, the war — in the
    view of the CIA, among others — was stalemated.</s>
   </p>

   <aside><s>JSOC is the single most truly joint command within the U.S.
   military.</s></aside>

   <p>
    <s rank='.4'>But JSOC had just experienced its finest hour — the
    fulfillment of the ultimate goal of McChrystal’s <keyword
    name='network'>networking</keyword> strategy.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>A Navy SEAL team killed Osama bin Laden.</s>
    <s>The mission was planned by McRaven; ultimately quarterbacked by CIA
    Director Leon Panetta; and relied extensively on both CIA analysis and
    JSOC’s years of raiding in Afghanistan.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>What was bureaucratically unthinkable before McChrystal is now
    routine: JSOC and CIA, matched with other government elements, now hunt
    al-Qaida worldwide in expanding, secretive wars.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s>Nor is that likely to change.</s>
    <s>McChrystal’s allies and proteges are all over the security
    bureaucracy.</s>
    <s>McRaven now runs all U.S. Special Operations Forces.</s>
    <s>Petraeus now runs the CIA.</s>
    <s>McChrystal’s fellow Army Ranger, Lt. Gen. Joseph Votel, now runs
    JSOC.</s>
    <s rank='.8'>Ten years after 9/11, al-Qaida’s <keyword
    name='network'>network</keyword> looks more brittle than ever, while JSOC’s
    is robust.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.8'>The <keyword name='network'>network</keyword> McChrystal
    built, McRaven enhanced and Votel inherits comes in stark contrast to the
    rest of the U.S.  security bureaucracy, which Priest and Arkin call “Top
    Secret America” and which remains disconnected, bloated and expensive.</s>
    <s>Priest and Arkin bluntly conclude that McChrystal turned JSOC around “by
    outright rejecting at least four of Top Secret America’s defining
    characteristics: its enormous size, its counterproductive duplication, its
    internal secrecy, and its old-fashioned, hierarchical structure.”</s>
    <s>What the post-9/11 reforms failed to accomplish across the sprawling
    national security apparatus, McChrystal did in miniature.</s>
   </p>

   <p>
    <s rank='.8'>“We had to figure out a way to retain our traditional
    capabilities of professionalism, technology, and, when needed, overwhelming
    force,” McChrystal recalled in Foreign Policy, “while achieving levels of
    knowledge, speed, precision, and unity of effort that only a <keyword
    name='network'>network</keyword> could provide.”</s>
    <s>It didn’t work in Afghanistan with conventional forces.</s>
    <s rank='.9'>But now it’s up to the secretive, lethal <keyword
    name='network'>network</keyword> that McChrystal established to finally
    destroy the terrorist <keyword name='network'>network</keyword> that
    inspired it.</s>
   </p>
  </section>
 </body>
</document>
